Okay, today's דף daf is כ"ה chaf hey 25. We pick up
at the bottom of כ"ד עמוד ב'. chaf dalet amud bet.
And we have been looking at this issue about when do you
need to use the right hand. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
you don't need to use it for the קבלת הדם. Kabbalas ha-Dam.
It had something to, and clearly for him the question was with
this word באצבעו be-etzba'o in a פסוק pasuk that talks about catching
the blood and placing it, is it going on the first half
or the second half of the פסוק? pasuk? But what's clear for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is that it's determined by the word אצבע.
etzba. Whereas the גמרא's Gemara current claim, although whatever, could have been
otherwise, the גמרא's Gemara current claim is that for the חכמים Chachamim
it goes either by the word אצבע etzba or the word כהן.
Kohen. So for example, right, we have the idea here that the,
so everybody agrees that by the חטאת Chatas the placing of the
blood is, requires אצבע etzba because it says באצבעו ונתן. be-etzba'o ve-natan.
Right, the question is does the catching of the blood need it
because it says ולקח הכהן? ve-lakach ha-Kohen? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says that doesn't need it. The חכמים Chachamim say it does. Right,
the עולה Olah does the throwing of the blood need, need the
right hand? It says וזרק הכהן. ve-zarak ha-Kohen. It doesn't say the
word אצבע. etzba. So again, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that doesn't
need the right hand. The חכמים Chachamim say it does need the
right hand. Okay, so the חכמים Chachamim say the word כהן Kohen
also means the right hand and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says only
the word אצבע. etzba. The other thing that we mentioned, which we
didn't explain how we know according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, is
the idea of the קמיצה. Kemitza. Okay, because everybody agrees, right, וקמץ
הכהן, ve-kamatz ha-Kohen, everybody agrees, so there the keyword is כהן, Kohen,
but there everybody agrees that that does need the right hand. So
we haven't figured out why that's true for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Okay, but here רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says שמאל. smol. And here
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can do it with the שמאל.
smol. All right, so that's where we're up to. Okay, and here
everybody says you need ימין. yamin. We haven't, it's not exactly clear
why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that the קמיצה Kemitza requires ימין.
yamin. Let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
bottom of כ"ד עמוד ב'. chaf dalet amud bet. אלא
הא דאמר רבא, Ella had d'amar Rava, four lines from the bottom.
אלא הא דאמר רבא, Ella had d'amar Rava, that which רבא Rava
said: יד יד לקמיצה, yad yad le-kemitza,
רגל רגל לחליצה, regel regel le-chalitza, אוזן אוזן לרצועה. ozen ozen le-retzu'a.
So by again the מצורע, Metzora, which is where we learn out
a lot of these ideas of requiring the right hand, so there's
a פסוק pasuk that the גמרא Gemara seems, sees as like an
unnecessary, superfluous פסוק pasuk where it says by, it says that the
כהן Kohen should put it על תנוך אוזן הימנית ועל בוהן ידו
הימנית ועל בוהן רגלו הימנית, al tenuch ozen ha-yemanit ve-al bohen yado
ha-yemanit ve-al bohen raglo ha-yemanit, right, so the ear, you know, the
right lobe of the ear, and the right hand, and you know,
and the thumb of the right hand, and the toe of the
right foot. So the גמרא Gemara sees all that as extra and
says we can learn out from those that not only do those
require the right, but those parts of the body elsewhere also require
to be, to be done with the right. So what would that
be? So he says the following. So here's what רבא Rava says:
יד יד לקמיצה. yad yad le-kemitza. So when it says on the
thumb of the right hand, that's telling you that the קמיצה Kemitza
requires a right hand. Okay, if so, that, that's what that extra
פסוק pasuk is telling you. רגל רגל, regel regel, when it tells
you the toe of the right foot, that you can learn that
out not only by a מצורע Metzora but לחליצה, le-chalitza, when you
do the act of חליצה, chalitza, it's the shoe from the right
foot. אוזן אוזן, ozen ozen, when it says the lobe of the
right ear, it's not only telling you that for the מצורע Metzora
but also לרציעה, le-retzi'ah, by the guy who wants to be an
עבד, eved, you know, after the six years he wants to stay
a slave and you pierce his ear, it's the right ear. So
רבא Rava says we learn from this that all these other places
which are unclear also need the right. The problem is, why is
קמיצה Kemitza unclear? We have the word כהן. Kohen. Okay, now for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's actually a great גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah,
because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon could say, I don't learn from כהן.
Kohen. Thank you, רבא, Rava, you just helped me understand, you know,
establish why קמיצה's Kemitza the right hand because of this גזירה שוה
gezerah shavah of יד יד. yad yad. Okay, or for the extra
יד yad is to tell you that קמיצה, Kemitza, right, because it
says, to tell me that the יד yad of קמיצה's Kemitza the
right hand. But for the חכמים Chachamim they already learned it out
from the word כהן. Kohen. So why did they also need this
יד yad of רבא Rava to tell you right hand by
קמיצה? Kemitza? Alright, so that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says,
חד לקומץ וחד לקידוש קומץ, chad le-kometz ve-chad le-kiddush kometz,
because there's two stages of the process, right? The two stages of
the process are,
here's the guy who brings his מנחה, Mincha, okay, here, this is
the owner, he brings his מנחה, Mincha, pretty
big כלי. kli. Okay, and here's the כהן Kohen and the כהן
Kohen takes the קומץ. kometz. Okay, so that's the קמיצה. Kemitza. He
takes it, puts his hand in and takes the קומץ kometz out.
Then what does he do with it? That's stage number one. Stage
number two is, here's the כהן Kohen and he's got the קמיצה.
Kemitza. in his hand, and he now puts it, now because they
both need a right hand, you probably need, you need another כהן,
Kohen, he now puts it in the hand, in of the כלי,
Kli, the כלי שרת. Kli Sharet. Remember we said how a כלי
שרת Kli Sharet sanctifies? Okay, and the same way, you know, it's
sort of like this what it's similar to is if you've got
an animal, okay, you've got the whatever, you've got the שחיטה, Shechita,
okay, with the knife, okay, you've got the שחיטה, Shechita, and here's
the blood, and here's the קבלה, Kabbalah, right, קבלת הדם, Kabbalas Hadam,
right? Okay, so, okay, so this is sort of the taking it
out and this is the catching of it, right? That's, so this
is like the שחיטה, Shechita, you're taking out the קומץ, Kometz, and
now you're putting it into the כלי, Kli, that's like the קבלה.
Kabbalah.
Okay, so he takes a little bit of it out of that
hand? He does, out of his hand and puts it onto the?
No, the whole, the whole קומץ, Kometz, the whole hand-breadth. But rather
than taking it from the thing and then walking it up the
altar and dropping it on the altar, what we do is we
take the קומץ, Kometz, which is like the שחיטה, Shechita, and then
you put it in the כלי, Kli, which is like the קבלת
הדם, Kabbalas Hadam, and then you bring that to the altar and
you put that on the altar, okay? And that's part of this
idea that we also learned the other day how כלי שרת Klei
Shares is מקדשים. Mekadeshim. That you need the stuff to go into
a כלי שרת, Kli Sharet, for stuff that was brought from the
house, the animal or the whatever, it's going into the כלי שרת
Kli Sharet which raises its level of sanctity which now allows it
to be offered up on the altar. Okay, so that's, anyway, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. There's two acts. This has to
be with the right hand and getting it in the כלי שרת.
Kli Sharet. The כהן Kohen here who's holding the כלי שרת Kli
Sharet has to be holding it in his right hand. The same
way here, the קבלת הדם Kabbalas Hadam has to be in the
right hand. Okay, so that's why you need an extra יד. Yad.
כהן Kohen tells you one part of the קמיצה, Kemitza, this, and
the extra יד Yad tells you this part of the קמיצה. Kemitza.
The קבלה Kabbalah part of the קמיצה Kemitza has to be in
the right hand. Okay? חדא לקומץ וחדא לקידוש קומץ. Chada lekometz vechada
lekidush kometz. And now the גמרא Gemara says,
ולרבי שמעון דלא בעי קידוש קומץ. Ule-Rebbi Shimon delo baei kidush kometz.
Now רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does not require, there's another גמרא Gemara
that we haven't seen yet, but there's a גמרא Gemara that says
that according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon you could just take the
hand-breadth and walk it up the altar and put it straight on
the altar. You don't need this part, but the whole hand-breadth, not
just a little bit of it, but the whole thing that's in
your hand.
No, I thought he kept, because I thought he put part off
and he kept the rest for himself.
No, no. The rest that's for himself is the rest that's left
in here. That's the שיריים. Shirayim. Okay, that's what he didn't take.
Okay, so you certainly do the whole hand-breadth. But according to רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon in a different גמרא, Gemara, there's an opinion that
according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon you could walk it straight to
the altar and put the whole thing. You don't do this part.
Okay? So if he doesn't need that, okay, ולמאן דאמר לרבי שמעון
בעי קידוש קומץ, Ule-man de-amar le-Rebbi Shimon baei kidush kometz, now even
if רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon required this stage, required this stage, קומץ
בשמאל שרי מכשיר, Kometz bismol sharei machshir, he would say that using
the left hand is okay. How do we know this? Okay, here's
a little pop quiz everybody. How could we know that רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon would say that the כהן Kohen who's holding the כלי
שרת Kli Sharet that this כהן Kohen puts the קומץ Kometz in,
that this guy can use his left hand? How can you just
assume that that would be correct? That for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
this guy can use his left hand?
Doesn't say it's?
Well, okay, it doesn't say it, okay, but also, where do we
know clearly רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you can use a left
hand?
For the קבלת הדם. Kabbalas Hadam. Okay? And this is, even if
it's required and it's not as explicit in the תורה Torah that
it's required, it parallels the קבלת הדם. Kabbalas Hadam. So if רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you can use your left hand here, then
he says you can use your left hand here. So for רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon there would only be one act that would require
right hand, which would be this. This either act doesn't occur, either
you can just take the hand-breadth straight to the altar, or if
it does occur, clearly the left hand is okay. Didn't they?
But would the rabbis disagree about the left hand on the... oh
wait, it's the שחיטה Shechita that is not, this is the second
stage, the?
Right, this is the קבלת הדם, Kabbalas Hadam, right, right.
Okay. Alright, so, okay, so now so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does
not require this on the left, you know, does not require, this,
this can be either not required or with the left hand. Only
one thing is the right hand, this. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, so יד יד דרבה למה לי? Yad yad
deRabba lama li? So why do you need the יד יד Yad
yad of רבה? Rabba? The only thing that requires the right hand
for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is this. Now there's an obvious answer
why you need the יד יד Yad yad of רבה. Rabba. Cause
how do we know this is a right hand? Cause of הכהן,
Hakohen, right? רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon doesn't, doesn't use the דרשה Drasha
of הכהן. Hakohen. So it's actually perfect. He should use the יד
יד, Yad yad, you know, to say that this is the right
hand and this doesn't need a right hand but this does, that
should be the יד יד. Yad yad. So we should actually be
able to end right here, period. But the גמרא Gemara says there's
another way we know that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon requires the right
hand for the קמיצה. Kemitza. How do we know that? אי לקמיצה
עצמה, Ei lekemitza atzmah, maybe you'll say he needs the יד יד
Yad yad for the very act of קמיצה Kemitza because he can't
learn it out from הכהן. Hakohen. But if that's true, so מדרב
יהודה בריה דרב חייא נפקא. Mi-deRav Yehuda brei deRav Chiya nafka. He
can learn that from a different teaching. Okay? So he doesn't use...
he doesn't need יד יד Yad yad for this. Because this doesn't
take place or can be a left hand, he should need יד
יד yad yad for this, because he doesn't learn it from כהן,
Kohen, but we're going to learn from a different place that he
already knows that this is the right hand. So then we're going
to be left with the question: what do you do with the
יד יד? yad yad? So where do we know from this other
place that this requires—I mean, did I say left? I meant right.
Where do we know from the other place that this requires the
right hand? Let's take a look. מדרב יהודה בריה דרב חייא נפקא.
mi-D'Rav Yehuda breih d'Rav Chiya nafka. דאמר רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא:
d'amar Rav Yehuda breih d'Rav Chiya: מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? mai ta'ama
d'Rebbi Shimon? Okay, what is the reason of רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon?
Not the רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon we're dealing with; רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon had a lot to say about קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, he's like
always the
counter-voice, you know, the counter-voice by a lot of these issues. So
the רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon he's talking about is the following, okay.
David there brings his קמיצה, kemitzah, his מנחה mincha to me, the
כהן. Kohen. Okay, and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, I, the כהן,
Kohen, have two options.
Either I can go ahead and take it with my right hand
and do the קמיצה kemitzah with my right hand and then walk
that up onto the altar and put it straight on without the
כלי, kli, like we talked about another way. Okay, or, that's one
version. Or, if I choose to, I can take it and put
it in a כלי, kli, right? To this question: do you need
this stage? He says for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon you got two
choices. You could do it without that, but then you gotta use
your right hand and put it on the altar with your right
hand. If you go ahead and put it into this כלי kli
and do that stage, then you can put it onto the altar,
you can use your left hand to put it onto the altar.
So why is that? Now, before we explain what verse he learns
that from, okay, I want you to understand conceptually what רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is saying, because this is a repeating theme, which is
about the כהן Kohen is like a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Okay,
so the point is like this: if you want the כהן, Kohen,
if you want to use a כלי שרת, kli sharet, the כלי
שרת kli sharet sanctifies it. The actual act of putting it on
the altar does not require a right hand. That act, you know,
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon in general, as we've seen, is not so—has
a lot of places he doesn't need the right hand. The act
of קבלה kabbalah doesn't need a right hand, you know, other types
of things, זריקה zrika here doesn't need a right hand. So if
the זריקה zrika of an עולה olah doesn't need a right hand,
for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it could be a left, the putting
of the קומץ kometz of the מנחה mincha on the altar doesn't
need a right hand. So if you got it in a כלי,
kli, then go ahead and put it on the altar with your
left hand, be my guest. Okay, but if you're not going to
use a כלי, kli, then what's going to sanctify this קומץ? kometz?
You know what's going to sanctify it? The hand of the כהן.
Kohen. The hand of the כהן Kohen is the substitute of the
כלי. kli. And if you want the hand of the כהן Kohen
to be, to function like a כלי, kli, that's where we need
the right hand. You don't need the right hand in the עבודה,
avodah, the act of putting it on the altar, okay, you know,
maybe by the חטאת chatas you do or whatever, but by other
things you don't. But you need the right hand if you're not
using a כלי, kli, because then you need the כהן's Kohen's body
to function like the כלי. kli. Very, very elegant idea. Okay, so
let's—so now he says where do we learn that, where does רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon get that idea from the פסוק? pasuk? Okay,
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון—where mai ta'ama d'Rebbi Shimon does רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon get this idea? דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, the verse says: קודש
קדשים היא, kodesh kodashim hi, this is what it says by the
מנחה, mincha, it is holy of holies,
כחטאת וכאשם, k'chatas v'k'asham, like the חטאת chatas and like the אשם.
asham. So what does that mean? It means the following. בא לעובדה
ביד עובדה בימין כחטאת בא לעובדה בכלי עובדה בשמאל כאשם. ba l'ovdah
b'yad ovdah b'yamin k'chatas, ba l'ovdah b'kli ovdah b'smol k'asham. So why
are we comparing it both to a חטאת chatas and an אשם?
asham? Like, just compare it to one of them. So
no. בא לעובדה ביד עובדה בימין כחטאת, ba l'ovdah b'yad ovdah b'yamin
k'chatas, בא לעובדה בכלי עובדה בשמאל כאשם. ba l'ovdah b'kli ovdah b'smol
k'asham. So remember, here's the key: what is the one place that
we have seen so far that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon clearly agrees
you need the right hand? You know the one place he clearly
agrees you need the right hand? By the placing of the blood
of a חטאת. chatas. The one place it's clear, right? He doesn't
need it for the קבלה kabbalah of the blood of a חטאת,
chatas, he doesn't need it about the זריקה zrika of the דם
dam of the עולה. olah. The one place he clearly needs it
is about the placing of the blood of the חטאת. chatas. So
therefore, and what's parallel to the placing of the blood of the
חטאת? chatas? The putting of the קומץ kometz on the altar. So
he says here's why the פסוק pasuk says that the מנחה mincha
is like a חטאת chatas and like an אשם. asham. There are
ways, there are times where you would need to treat it like
a חטאת chatas and only put it on the altar with your
right hand. You know what that is? When you're not using a
כלי. kli. When you're not using a כלי, kli, that's when we're
going to demand the right hand and treat it like a חטאת.
chatas. When you are using your כלי, kli, so the same way
an אשם asham or any other קרבן korban you can throw the
blood with your left hand according to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, so
therefore here too, if you're going to not—if you're going to agree
to use a כלי, kli, then you can go ahead and use
your left hand. Okay, it's a very elegant read of the verse.
Sometimes it's like a חטאת, chatas, right hand; sometimes it's like other
קרבנות. korbanot. Within רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, only a חטאת chatas really
needs the right hand; other things don't really need the right hand,
even for putting on the altar. All right, so that's his idea,
that this מנחה mincha depends if you're using your direct hand, then
it has to be the right. If you're using the כלי, kli,
then the same way the עולה olah the blood can be with
your left hand, the מנחה mincha can be with
your left hand.
If you're holding the כלי Kli with your left hand which is
holding the blood,
this is my כלי, Kli,
I got the blood in here, how am I getting it on
the wall of the altar, like that with my left hand or
like that with my right hand?
Okay, you're going to toss it.
Yeah, exactly.
The כלי Kli is small enough that you can do it
with one hand, it sounds like it, yeah. I mean, I would
wonder about that too, especially it's heavy with the blood. I don't,
that's a good question. I've been wondering about that as well. I
wonder if you can use the other hand to support if you
need, but okay.
What about when they're talking about putting the blood onto the corners?
That's the חטאת Chatas and that's more with your finger, that was
with the כלי, Kli, yeah exactly, and that's exactly the parallel, thank
you for pointing that out. The חטאת, Chatas, which is with the
right, is also because you're using your finger. Okay, and that's again
the word אצבע. Etzba. So what he's saying is if you want
to use, do this מנחה Mincha and you want to use just
your hands, okay, like the way you use your finger by the
חטאת, Chatas, if your hand is the focus and not the כלי,
Kli, then it's got to be your right hand. The same way
here it's your right because you're using your finger, if you're going
to use with this מנחה Mincha just your hand, it's got to
be your right hand. If however you want to use a כלי,
Kli, okay, so you're right, I had that כלי Kli made that
point which is an excellent point, it's parallel also just in terms
of the physical nature of the act, right? Anything other, you know,
anything other than a חטאת Chatas you're getting the blood on the
altar with a כלי. Kli. So if you want to get this
part, this קומץ Kometz of the מנחה Mincha on the altar with
a כלי, Kli, I feel that when you're... I feel you can
use your left hand. And again because the כלי Kli is doing
the sanctifying or however you understand it, the focus is on the
כלי. Kli. So be my guest, use your left hand. That's what
you do by an עולה, Olah, that's what you do by an
אשם, Asham, you do that by a מנחה. Mincha. But if you
want to do straight with your own hand and not use a
כלי, Kli, similar to a חטאת Chatas that you place it straight
with your finger, then it has to be your right hand. Okay?
So that's a very elegant type of a דרשה Drasha for רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Anyway, the אפשאט Upshat of that דרשה Drasha is
that implicit in that is the idea that for a מנחה Mincha
when you are using your hand you need it to be your
right hand. That's what's implicit. If you're not going to use a
כלי Kli and you're going to put it with your hand, it's
got to be your right hand. So what the גמרא Gemara assumes
is once that's true and implicit in this דרשה Drasha that we
compare it to a חטאת Chatas and say when you're going to
use your hand it's got to be your right hand, he could...
we can infer from that that when you take the קומץ, Kometz,
which is obviously directly with your hand, that would also have to
be your right hand. So that's how רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon knows
that the קומץ Kometz has to be your right hand, not from
the word כהן, Kohen, okay, not from רבא'ס Rava's יד יד, Yad
Yad, although that could have been it, but from this beautiful little
דרשה Drasha that when you use your hand it's like a חטאת,
Chatas, it's your right hand, etc., when you use a כלי Kli
it's like everything else and it could be your left, okay, so
here you're using your hand, it's got to be your right hand.
Okay, so why do you need רבא'ס Rava's יד יד? Yad Yad?
We know where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon gets everything from, but why
do you need רבא'ס Rava's יד יד? Yad Yad? So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
לא נצרכה אלא לקומץ מנחת חוטא. Lo nitzrecha ela lekometz minchas chotei.
You're right, normal מנחה Mincha he knows you need your right hand
for everything we just said. But I might have thought when it
comes to a מנחה Mincha of a sinner, okay, which is basically
like, you know, like one example is an עולה ויורד, Olah V'yored,
the other is a case about, you
know, let's say the case of the עולה ויורד. Olah V'yored. Okay,
so anyway, so in that case where, you know, where it says
לא יצוק עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה... Lo yitzok aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levona...
but that's also by the, what do you call it? That's
by
סוטה. Sotah. במדבר, Bamidbar, right? ויקרא Vayikra 5:11.
ויקרא Vayikra 5:11. Okay, I think it's also by the סוטה. Sotah.
Okay, hold on.
ויקרא Vayikra 5:11. Yeah, thank you. So ואם לא תשיג ידו. V'im
lo sasig yado. So that's the עולה ויורד Olah V'yored if you
bring a מנחה Mincha for a חטא Cheit and it's the עולה
ויורד Olah V'yored and you're bringing the lowest, the מנחה, Mincha, it
says עשירית האיפה סלת לחטאת לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה
לבנה כי חטאת היא. Asiris ha'eifah soles l'chatas lo yasim aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levona ki chatas hee. As a חטאת Chatas you
don't adorn it, it's very simple, there's no oil, there's no לבונה.
Levona. I think the same is true by the way, let me
just check quickly by the סוטה, Sotah,
although there it's the מנחת קנאות, Minchas Kenaos, not a מנחת חוטא,
Minchas Chotei,
but it says like this. קמח שעורים לא יצוק עליו שמן
ולא יתן עליו לבונה כי מנחת קנאות הוא מנחת זכרון מזכרת עון.
kemach se'orim lo yitzok
alav shemen
v'lo yiten alav levonah ki minchas kanoat hu minchas zikaron mazkeres
avon.
So also because it's related to the suspicion of a sin, okay,
so those are two מנחות minchos that don't have the oil and
the frankincense. Okay, so Rabbi Shimon said, this is a little טעמא
דקרא, ta'ama dikra, you know, normally we don't use like, okay, you
know, little דרשות drashos about what the reason is, but here we're
saying he explains that why is it that it does not have
שמן shemen and לבונה? levonah? הוה אמר רבי שמעון, hava amar Rabbi
Shimon, טעמא דהאי, ta'ama d'hai, היינו אמר רבי שמעון שלא יהא קרבנו
מהודר. haynu amar Rabbi Shimon shelo yehei korbano mehudar. The explanation of
the פסוק, pasuk, you know, this really seems like sort of פשט
pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, okay, is that so but Rabbi Shimon
is bothered with is, here this person is a sinner, why do
we allow them to spend less money? They should have to spend,
you know, oil and frankincense cost a lot of money, a lot
more than flour and water. So why does—why do they get out
of having to spend that, you know, spend that on their קרבן?
korban? So really they should spend that on their קרבן. korban. But
it's more important that the קרבן korban should not be beautiful and
adorned because it's a קרבן korban of a sinner. So therefore because
the Torah is sort of like downgrading this קרבן, korban, it's a
funny הוה אמינא. hava amina. I would have thought סלקא דעתך אמינא,
salka datchon amina, so—so I would have thought כי קמץ ביד שמאל
נמי
תכשר. ki kamatz b'yad smol nami tichshar. Maybe the Torah's like, yeah,
it's only a sinner's קרבן, korban, we're going to treat it very
like, you know, very marginally, we're not going to, you know, we're
going to let it, so it's second grade. So maybe therefore we
would allow it even with the left hand? קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that that's not the case. Okay. It's a very funny
הוה אמינא. hava amina. What would the fact it not be beautiful
be connected to the idea that you can use your left hand?
But anyway. All right. So that's in the end the גמרא Gemara
says we need the יד יד yad yad to demand that we
need the right hand even for the מנחה mincha of a sinner.
But bottom line, what do we know? Let's review what we know.
For the חכמים, chachamim, you need your right hand pretty much for
everything. We haven't discussed שחיטה. shechita. Okay, but pretty much for everything
because they learn either from the word אצבע etzba or כהן, kohen,
and it pretty much says אצבע etzba and כהן kohen everywhere. The
one thing we don't need it for is like bringing the limbs
to the altar, which is not part of the עיקר כפרה ikar
kapara process. It's not part of the blood and the עיקר כפרה
ikar kapara process. Okay. But the חכמים chachamim sort of need it
for everything. Rabbi Shimon is the more interesting position. He says I'm
only going to need it where it says אצבע. etzba. I'm going
to need it for the placing of the blood on the corners
of the altar, whatever, by the חטאת, chatas, not for the catching
of the blood, not for the throwing of the blood by the
other קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. By the מנחה, mincha, you know, receiving the
מנחה mincha in the כלי, kli, if you do that according to
Rabbi Shimon, is like the catching of the blood. That doesn't need
right hand.
Putting, taking, putting of the—the one thing that does need the right
hand for him is the taking of the מנחה, mincha, the taking
of it. That's interesting that for him that does, because you know,
the only thing we have other than that is the blood of
the חטאת. chatas. So that is the one thing that does need
the right hand, the taking of it. Okay. And now what we
find out is maybe what that has a lot to do with
for Rabbi Shimon is the things that use directly the body of
the כהן. kohen. That's the common denominator. Okay. So this needs—is directly
the body of the כהן. kohen. This is in a כלי. kli.
This is—the catching is in a כלי. kli. The throwing is in
a כלי. kli. The thing that is directly the body of the
כהן kohen is the placing of the finger. So similarly, the thing
that's directly the body of the כהן kohen by the מנחה mincha
is the taking of it. That does need the right. How about
the putting of the קומץ kometz on the altar? That depends. If
you're going to put it straight with your hand, that's like the
putting with your finger with the—with the חטאת. chatas. That's directly the
body of the כהן. kohen. That needs a right hand. If you're
going to put it in a כלי kli and from the כלי
kli you're going to put it on the altar, if that's not
directly with your body, that's through a כלי, kli, you do not
need your right hand. So at the end of the day, after
you get through all the דרשות, drashos, Rabbi Shimon's point is a
simple one. If it's directly the body of a כהן, kohen, it
has to be the right. If it's with a כלי, kli, it
can be the left. Okay. And as I said, I think the
interesting point is, is that conceptually the עבודה avodah can be with
the left. The act can be with the left. But what—but—but if
you need the כהן kohen in—if it's the—if it's only the body
of the כהן, kohen, then that's the כהן kohen as a כלי
שרת, kli shares, that has to be the right hand of the
כהן. kohen. That—if there's a vessel, then it doesn't. But if you
need the כהן kohen to act like a כלי שרת, kli shares,
that's like the right hand of the כהן. kohen. That sort of
seems to be the logic. Okay. Let's take a look now at
the next משנה. mishnah.
Shifting gears a little. That was the end of a, you know,
fascinating discussion of right versus left. That was the question about like
what's the status of a כהן? kohen? Is he an אונן? onen?
Is he—is he drunk? Is he this? Is he—using his—but when you
got to the right and left hand, that was less the status
of the כהן kohen and it was more how is the act
of the עבודה avodah performed? So now we're going to continue with
that and talking about the act of the performance and certain things
that sort of
invalidate the עבודה avodah if things go wrong. Okay, so let's take
a look. נשפך הדם על הרצפה ואספו פסול. nishpach hadam al haritzpa
v'asfo pasul.
Let's say the blood, you שחט shachted it, and it went straight,
the animal, and you—and the blood went straight from the animal's neck
and hit the ground. And then you mopped it up from the
ground. You can't use that blood. But that's in contrast to a
case where you שחט shachted it, you caught
the blood... Once it was caught in the vessel, then even if
it spilled, you can regather it and put it back and put
it on the altar. So the basic הלכה halacha is is that
the blood has to go from the neck of the animal into
the vessel. It has to be caught by the כלי שרת. kli
shareis. If it's not caught by the כלי שרת, kli shareis, it's
invalid. If it's caught by the כלי שרת kli shareis and afterwards
spilled, you can put it back into the כלי שרת. kli shareis.
So where do we know this from? Let's look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught: ולקח הכהן המשיח מדם
הפר. V'lakach hakohen hamashiach midam hapar. He should take from the blood
of the cow. Okay, so and we're obviously going to just generalize
this פסוק pasuk to our cases. מדם הנפש. Midam hanefesh.
Okay, so it says הפר, hapar, somehow like the ox, the thing
that represents the entirety of the ox, the soul blood, okay. ולא
מדם העור, V'lo midam haor, not some like bleeding from some cut
in the skin. It has to be come, you know, from the
what are those major arteries called? The jugular vein. It's a vein,
right? It has to be like coming from the jugular, it has
to be coming from the life blood, not like from some some
blood that's from some cut in the skin. ולא מדם התמצית. V'lo
midam hatamtzit. Now דם התמצית dam hatamtzit is like the blood that's
like the remnant blood. The Rabbis understand that as soon as when
you immediately cut it, you get the full, you know, sort of
pressure and the force, and then afterwards it like dribbles out more
and the color's different, and that other stuff afterwards it's called דם
התמצית. dam hatamtzit. Obviously it's all part of a closed system, it's
all the same, you know, chemically it's all the same blood. Okay,
but what it represents is it has to sort of like represent,
you know, the you know, life force. Okay, so that's so that's
the blood that you need is that stuff that comes from the
jugular and not the the like the initial like really pressured, you
know, squirting out. ולא מדם התמצית. V'lo midam hatamtzit. Now that's one
point. Now get back to our point
about that it has to be caught by a כלי שרת. kli
shareis. מדם הפר, Midam hapar, דם מהפר יקבלנו. dam mehapar yekablenu. We
play around with the word with the מ. mem. Okay, we say
מדם הפר, midam hapar, take the מ mem from the word דם
dam and read it דם מהפר. dam mehapar. Not from the blood
of the ox, but דם מהפר. dam mehapar. The blood has to
come
straight has to be caught straight from the ox. The דם dam
has to be מהפר. mehapar. It has to be coming not off
of the floor, it has to come off of the ox. Okay,
דם מהפר יקבלנו. Dam mehapar yekablenu. די סלקא דעתך Di salka da'atach
now די סלקא דעתך מדם הפר כדכתיב. Di salka da'atach midam hapar
kidechtiv. Now
what justifies reading it that way? Maybe we should just read it
literally, the blood of the ox. Okay, no. מדם ואפילו מקצת דם,
Midam v'afilu miktzat dam, and then we read the מ mem in
the following way. What's the מ mem doing? Right? הפר, hapar, right,
is sort of saying the, you know,
right? מדם הפר. midam hapar. So the first הפר, hapar, like it
represents the whole the whole ox, is דם הנפש. dam hanefesh. Okay,
that's one דרשה. drasha. Okay, that's the ה, hey, the ox, the
thing that represents the fullness of the ox, דם הנפש. dam hanefesh.
What we want to know is what are you going to do
with this מ? mem? So what we're doing is we're reading it
דם מהפר dam mehapar and it has to come straight from it.
But the other thing you could do with that מ mem is
the way we sometimes read a מ mem is מדם, midam, even
some of the blood. It doesn't even have to be all the
blood. As long as you catch some of the blood, you're okay.
All right? So maybe that's the way we should read the מ.
mem.
די סלקא דעתך Di salka da'atach where were
we די סלקא דעתך מדם הפר כדכתיב מדם ואפילו מקצת דם, Di
salka da'atach midam hapar kidechtiv midam v'afilu miktzat dam, even some of
the blood. ואמר רב השוחט צריך שיקבל כל דמו של פר. V'amar
Rav hashochet tzarich sheyekabel kol damo shel par. No, you have to
catch all of the blood. Now that's
לכתחילה, lechatchila, okay? בדיעבד Bedi'avad you don't have to, but anyway, you're
supposed to catch all the blood, שנאמר ואת כל דמו ישפוך. shene'emar
v'et kol damo yishpoch. All of the blood you should spill. Okay,
so, which means you have to have caught all of it to
begin with. All right? אלא, Ela, so therefore the מ mem here
should not be read to mean only some is okay, although בדיעבד
bedi'avad it's true that even if you only caught some it's okay,
but we would prefer not to read the מ mem to be
making that point, and therefore how are we going to read it?
אלא מדם הפר דם מהפר יקבלנו. Ela midam hapar dam mehapar yekablenu.
We move the מ mem to the other word. וקסבר גורעין ומוסיפין
ודורשין. V'kasavar gorin umosifin vedorshin. So this is great. גורעין, Gorin, you
take the מ mem away from here, ומוסיפין, umosifin, you add it
over there to the מהפר, mehapar, ודורשין, vedorshin, and then you make
the דרשה drasha you wanted to make. Okay? So this is גורעין,
gorin, you remove the מ mem from here, ומוסיפין, umosifin, you add
it here,
דם מהפר, dam mehapar, and the blood has to come straight from
the ox and that's and not off of the floor. Okay.
Now גופא, Gufa, let's go back and look at that earlier statement.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב השוחט צריך שיקבל כל דמו של פר
שנאמר ואת כל דם הפר ישפך. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav hashochet
tzarich sheyekabel kol damo shel par shene'emar v'et kol dam hapar yishapech.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא בשיריים כתיב. V'ha beshirayim ktiv.
One minute, but when it says spill all the blood, it's talking
about the blood that's left over after you put the blood on
the altar. So clearly it's not all the blood. It means all
the remaining blood, but it doesn't mean all the blood. So the
גמרא Gemara says, alright, אם אינו עניין לשיריים דהא לית להו לכוליה
דם. Im eino inyan lishirayim daha leit lehu l'kulei dam. You're right,
but since כל הדם kol hadam cannot really be referred to to
the spilling of the remnant, because you don't have all the blood
by the time you get to the remnant, so תנהו ענין בקבלה.
t'nayeihu inyan b'kabbalah. It's telling you that there's some act that requires
you to receive all the blood, that requires all the blood, and
what requires all the blood? The catching of the blood, obviously, that's
where you know, that's where it would be demanded. All right, אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: השוחט צריך שיגביה
סכין למעלה. hashocheit tzarich sheyagbi'a sakin l'ma'alah. The guy shechting the animal
after he finished the שחיטה, shechitah, he has to like, you know,
move his knife away. Why does he have to move his knife
away? Because if he keeps his knife there above the vessel that's
underneath the neck that's catching the blood of the animal, what's going
to happen?
שנאמר ולקח מדם הפר ולא מדם הפר ודבר אחר. Shene'emar v'lakach midam
hapar v'lo midam hapar v'davar acher. ודם... v'dam... okay,
so what's going to happen? There's blood went straight from the neck
onto the knife, right? If that blood goes from the knife into
the כלי שרת, kli sharet, it's not going straight from the animal
into the כלי שרת. kli sharet. So that's a little bit, now
you might think that's a little bit better than hitting the floor,
because that sort of blood hasn't like, you know, sort of like,
it hasn't like completed its, you know, maybe you see it as
a process, right? It banged off the knife and went from the
knife, but nevertheless the גמרא's Gemara saying that's just as bad as
the blood from the floor. Okay, that did not go straight from,
you know, the neck to the, you know, to the כלי שרת,
kli sharet, and therefore in order to prevent that blood from dripping
into the כלי שרת, kli sharet, you gotta keep on, keep the
motion and keep moving it away from the, you know, away from
where the כלי שרת kli sharet is. השוחט צריך שיגביה שנאמר ולקח
מדם הפר ולא מדם הפר ודבר אחר. hashocheit tzarich sheyagbi'a shene'emar v'lakach
midam hapar v'lo midam hapar v'davar acher. ודם סכין במאי מקנח ליה?
V'dam sakin b'mai m'kaneich lei? Now where do you wipe the blood
off? Presumably you have to do another שחיטה, shechitah, you don't want
a dirty knife, and I don't know why the גמרא Gemara couldn't
imagine that you just had like a lot of rags there, you
know, but anyway, so אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: בשפת מזרק. b'sfat mizrak.
So by the outer edge, רש״י Rashi says, of the of the
מזרק mizrak is the כלי שרת. kli sharet. So it's a little
bit bizarre. You don't want it mixing into the blood in the
כלי שרת, kli sharet, but what you do is you sort of
just, you know, you wipe it, you know, I really don't get
it, I have to say, because like it's one thing if you
can use like the inner lip, you know, you can sort of
create some tension and like whatever, scrape it off like that. To
do it like on the outside lip seems like a funny way
and also seems dangerous. It seems like a way, dangerous, halachically dangerous,
you know, not that you're going to cut yourself. But, you know,
it seems like a way that the blood could accidentally get back
in. It would seem like why not just have a rag? You
know, I really, I really don't understand this so well.
Because it's not clean, then that blood will mix the next time
you do.
No, I understand why you have to clean it.
No, no, but I don't know that that's going to totally clean.
Right, you mean it won't totally clean. A rag'll do a much
better job. Yeah, I really don't understand. It seems like, it seems
like it's risky halachically and it's not going to do the right
job. Do they say anything in your notes there?
Just have some rags in בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
But maybe it's just the bowls were so called.
Yeah, I know, they're called, right, רש״י Rashi says the word מזרק,
mizrak, that's the next line of the גמרא, Gemara, כדיכתיב כפורי זהב.
k'dichtiv
kiporei zahav.
So the word כפור, kipor, לכפר, l'chaper, can mean to clean. So
רש״י Rashi is saying that the meaning of the word that it
calls these bowls כפורי kiporei is that it's also to say you
would clean your knife on them. But practically, I don't really understand
it. You know, you just have some rags there with some rags.
Anyway, אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, when you get to the
practical part,
but what if the blood drips down, let's say he wipes it
on the on the edge, and then it hits the floor, doesn't
matter.
Yeah, because that blood isn't being used. The other question to ask
is let's say a little of that blood goes into it and
then you get interesting questions of ביטול. bitul. Like in this כלי
kli I caught like, you know, a gallon of the blood of
the animal and two drops from the knife fell in. Can I
use it or not? So that'll be like a ביטול bitul question
which we'll get to. Okay, so, אמר רב חסדא אמר רב ירמיה
בר אבא: Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Yirmiya bar Abba: השוחט צריך
שיתן ורידין, hashocheit tzarich sheyitein v'ridin, when you shecht it you have
to put the jugular, the veins, לתוך הכלי, l'toch hakli, into the
vessel. Now it doesn't literally mean into the vessel, like you take
the neck and you stick it into the vessel, but what it
means is it means above the vessel. Okay, so
here's your vessel and here's like the neck of the animal, okay,
that's just been cut off, and here's like the blood that's like
squirting out, okay, and basically it's got to be the neck and
with the veins of which the blood is coming out has to
be like directly on top of the vessel, looking at the air
space like over the vessel. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, it was also
taught, okay, and the reason is that, you know, it should be
directly caught from the, you know, from the neck, okay. Part of
the question would be also, we're going to see later, that, you
know, even the idea it has to come straight from the cow
is let's say it squirted, right, it squirted horizontally and then you
caught and then there was an arc, which is more natural, right?
And you were here catching it like after the horizontal squirt. So
then you're not directly catching it from the cow. You're getting it
from the air, right, as it were. You know what I'm saying?
Because it sort of moved this distance and then it came from
here. So therefore if you have to position it like this or
it's literally... directly coming straight from the neck of the cow. איתמר
נמי, itmar nami, it was also taught, אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן, amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, ורידים צריכים שיראו אויר כלי.
vridim tzerichim sheyiru avir kli. They have to be positioned directly over
the, you know, the hollow of the כלי. cli. בעי מיניה רב
אסי מרבי יוחנן, Ba'i minei Rav Assi meRabbi Yochanan, so Rav Assi
asked Rabbi Yochanan. היה מקבל
ונפחתו
שולי מזרק עד שלא הגיע דם לאויר מהו? Haya mekabel venifchetu shulei
mizrak ad shelo higia dam la'avir mahu? Okay, so here, okay, here
it is, I've got my, you know, you know, here's my vessel,
here's the neck, okay, of the animal, it's squirting in, the blood
is midair, it has not yet gotten into the airspace of my
vessel. The assumption is once it hits the airspace of my vessel,
even without hitting the floor of the vessel, that's considered caught by
the vessel. Because if you think about it, not all the blood
hits the floor anyway, only the initial blood hits the floor. So
as soon as it's in the airspace, it's caught by the vessel
and I'm done, I could spill it now and whatever. But before
it hit the airspace, let's actually assume that this is the blood,
this represents the stream of blood, before it hit, it was שחט
shechted over here, it's traveling through the air before it hit the
airspace of the vessel, but it's directly over, the bottom of it
falls out, of the vessel falls out. So is this considered to
have been caught by the vessel? When it was here, right, it
was going to be landing into a legitimate vessel. But before it
got there, the vessel stopped being a legitimate vessel to catch the
blood. So was that close? And so now if it was considered
like it was already caught, what's going to happen to this? Fine,
it's going to go in here and spill out, but then I
could collect it because it was already caught once it was here.
But if it's not yet considered already caught, right, then it's not
good. Logically you would think why should it be why should it
be considered already caught? You know, the thing fell out before it
got to the airspace. But let's see the גמרא's Gemara question.
It's accepted by going through that space.
Yeah, but not, but no, only when that space represents a כלי
cli that right could catch the blood. Right. So, אויר שאין סופו
לנוח כמינח דמי או לאו כמינח דמי? avir she'eino sofo lenuach kemunach
dami o lav kemunach dami?
If it's in the airspace, actually the airspace above the air of
the vessel, that means it's the airspace, like you know we talk
about a building has the air rights, so it's in the air
rights above the vessel in a way in which now we see
it never was going to land, you know land in the vessel.
Now that the bottom has fallen out, it's clear that it was
never ultimately going to fall into that vessel. Is it like it
legitimately went into the vessel or not? It seems no. But anyway,
אמר
ליה תניתוה, amar leh tanyatu'ah, we taught it. חבית שמונחת תחת הזינוק.
chavit shemuneches tachat hazinuk. Okay, now this is talking about a question
about using water for פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. It comes straight from
a wellspring, let's say, because it has to be מים חיים, mayim
chayim, okay, and it's going up and it is, well, you could
sort of use something similar to this. Here's your barrel, okay, here's
your, you know, here's your what do you call it, you've got
your, you know, pipe or whatever, you have your water from the
wellspring and it's traveling through this pipe, okay, this is all water
that could be used for פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, okay, and then
it's going to come out of this pipe and it's going to
all whatever, it's going to all go into this vessel. Now once
the water is in the vessel, in this barrel, I can't use
it for a פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, because then it's not מים
חיים, mayim chayim, then it's considered water from a vessel. It's not
water directly like from the wellspring. It's a similar type of an
idea. Okay, so let's take a look about when I can use
this water. Okay, תניתוה, tanyatu'ah, חבית שמונחת תחת הזינוק. chavit shemuneches tachat
hazinuk. So you have this barrel that's underneath the sort of the,
you know, the squirting of the the stream of water. מים שבתוכה,
mayim shebetocha, water that's in the vessel itself, in the barrel, is
already invalid for פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, ושבחוצה
לה פסולים. veshebechutza lah psulin. And even the water that's outside of
it is invalid, outside of it means that it's here in this
like airspace, okay, that's invalid. Alright, צריף פיה לזינוק. tzirif piha lezinuk.
Now let's say what you did rather was you actually,
I mean, so what you actually did was you put the barrel
up against, let's actually have this like this, okay, that's actually a
better example. Okay, so in the first case,
the first case was that the stuff that's חוצה לה chutza lah
is פסולים, psulin, that this water is פסול. pasul. Okay and that's
a case of
אויר כלי, avir kli, it's אויר כלי avir kli even once it
gets into that airspace, you can't catch that water and use it,
because once it's above the airspace above the above the barrel, it's
like it's in the barrel. So that's אויר כלי שסופו לנוח, avir
kli shesofo lenuach, the bottom of the barrel hasn't fallen out.
So how do you get any water if you can't collect it?
Well you could always go back to the well. I mean you
can't, you know, in this scenario you can't. Or you can remove
the barrel, you can put your, you can put your, you know,
your כלי cli that you're going to use for your פרה אדומה
Para Aduma here. But this is not a כלי kli that you
can use for your פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah.
Oh that's a non-oh.
This is this is just a barrel. Okay? It's a barrel. I
threw the word barrel. It's not a כלי kli okay? So therefore
you put your you put your כלי kli that you're going to
use for your פרה אדומה Parah Adumah here that's fine. But if
it's going into the barrel once it's in the barrel it's not
מים חיים mayim chayim and to catch it in mid-air since it's
heading to the barrel it's not מים חיים. mayim chayim. So that
case is no good. But if you moved your barrel up so
that it's now around the mouth of this right and this thing
sort of is like you know like that. Okay? Now obviously the
water there is invalid. Okay? But in that case
okay let's go on one minute.
סיפא פי הצינוק Seifa pi hatzinok מים שבתוכה פסולין mayim shebetochah pesulin
ושבחוצה לה כשרין v'shebechutzah lah kesherin that's on outside is kosher. Now
what does that mean? Let me just double check רש״י Rashi make
sure I'm explaining this correctly one minute.
Yes what רש״י Rashi says the problem is that the word חוצה
לה chutzah lah means something different in these two cases. But what
רש״י Rashi says here in this case the idea of I was
just checking that I got it right. In this case רש״י Rashi
says the חוצה לה chutzah lah means means you got the water
from the actual pipe itself let's say it's an open air pipe.
So in this type of a case right in this case
in this case right the water is in the air space above.
So if it's in the air space above it's invalid. Okay? But
in this case there is no air space. It goes straight into
the barrel. So the only way you're getting water other than water
from the barrel is going into the into the actual pipe itself
again assuming it's not like a totally sealed pipe. So in that
case since it's not in open air since it's basically in this
pipe that's not considered to be connected to the barrel. Only the
open air above the barrel is connected. If you were to actually
somehow grab it from while it's in the pipe that's that seems
to be the point of the second part of this right then
it's okay. All right so the upshot of this is is that
what we really care about is is that when it's in the
open air above the barrel it's like it's already in the barrel.
Okay when it's in the pipe if you get it straight from
the pipe somehow you're okay but if it's in the open air
it's like it's in the barrel. So the point is that's all
very nice but that just says when it's going to land in
the barrel. That's not our case when the floor is going to
fall out. So let's keep on reading. So it says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says הי מאי hei mai where were we?
What type of a proof is that? בעי מיניה אויר שאין סופו
לנוח baei minei avir she'ein sofo lanuach the question was about a
case where it wasn't going to eventually you know get caught by
the vessel because the floor fell out. וקא פשיט ליה אויר שסופו
לנוח v'ka pashit leh avir shesofo lanuach but then you tell me
oh look if you've got a good barrel with a good floor
in it then the air space above it's like it's already caught.
Great. That'll tell me the הלכה halachah like what happens if it's
going like this and the כלי kli is a totally good כלי
kli and let's say I don't know an interest a wind comes
along and pushes it away or something. Or somebody comes for me
an easier case somebody comes and knocks my hand and then falls
like that. That's actually an interesting question right? It was going to
land in the כלי kli the כלי kli is totally fine and
then at the last minute it got diverted. Okay? That's this case.
So maybe that's a good proof that that would be like it
was already caught in the כלי. kli. But that doesn't help me
for the case when the bottom of the כלי kli falls out.
All right? So then the גמרא Gemara says בעי מיניה אויר שאין
סופו לנוח וקא פשיט ליה אויר שסופו לנוח? baei minei avir she'ein
sofo lanuach v'ka pashit leh avir shesofo lanuach? So the גמרא Gemara
says תרתי קא בעי מיניה tartei ka baei minei actually it was
a double question. First question was what would be the story about
the air space if it would actually if the כלי kli was
okay? And again like an interesting scenario would be somebody knocked my
hand away at the last minute. Okay? That was question number one.
תרתי קא בעי מיניה tartei ka baei minei אם תמצא לומר אויר
שאין סופו לנוח לאו כמונח דמי im timtza lomar avir she'ein sofo
lanuach lav k'munach dami if you say when the bottom falls out
it's no
good אויר שסופו לנוח מאי avir shesofo lanuach mai what would be
the story if the bottom didn't fall out? And that's at least
a case that we could more see an argument that that would
be okay. The כלי kli remained totally fine. It was in the
air space directly above the כלי kli and then at the last
minute it didn't fall in the כלי. kli. Is it like it
already went into the כלי? kli? Okay? רב יוסף Rav Yosef so
that's one way of explaining the question and how this case of
the barrel answers that question. רב יוסף מתני הכי Rav Yosef matni
hachi that's how רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught the discussion. רב כהנא
מתני Rav Kahana matni רב כהנא Rav Kahana teaches differently. חבית
בעי מיניה ופשיט ליה חבית. chavit baei minei u'pashit leh chavit. It
wasn't about the question about the blood of a קרבן korban at
all. The question was about this whole discussion about the water to
use for a פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. He didn't know this משנה
*Mishnah*, okay, he wanted to know this question of water that's above
a barrel, can you use it for פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*? And
he quoted the משנה *Mishnah* and the משנה *Mishnah* says you can't
use it for פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*. Okay, totally different version of
the exchange. Okay, רבא מתני *Rava Masni*, and now רבא *Rava* has
a third version of the exchange. חביב בעי מיניה *Chaviv ba'ei minei*,
he wanted to know what is the story of this of airspace
directly above, if like for פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*, can you use
that? Is that like it's already in the vessel? Okay, ופשיט ליה
מזרק *u-pashit lei Mizrak*. And he learned his answer rather than the
way we did it, which is the question was about the blood
of a קרבן *korban* and we learned it from פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah*, this is the reverse way. The question was about the פרה
אדומה *Parah Adumah*, it's all the same question about the airspace above
a vessel, and he concluded it from the case of the blood,
from the vessel of the blood. How did he conclude it that
way? Because he says, listen, אי אתה מודה במזרק כי אפשר לו
בלא זינוק *ee atah modeh be-Mizrak ki efshar lo belo zinuk*. So
he says, and this is like the point that I said before,
okay, which is although again, I don't totally get this, okay, but
the argument is like this: Here's the כהן *Kohen* ready to receive
the blood, okay, here's the neck of the פרה *parah*. Now we
just said that the neck of the פרה *parah* has to be
directly above, right? And therefore it goes straight in. Okay, now, but
nevertheless says,
hold on, I'm just going to double-check רש"י
*Rashi*, make sure I'm getting this right.
Okay, so he says like this: Now,
again, I don't really get this, but here's the explanation. The explanation
is even though we're saying it's supposed to be directly over the
כלי *kli*, the reality is that the blood does not go straight
into the כלי *kli*. Like the blood will again, like sort of
squirt a little bit out, like you know, and like move maybe
in a different... I really don't get this. The reason I'm struggling
is I really don't understand it, because רש"י *Rashi* says that the
blood is sort of moving... the way it sounds like from רש"י
*Rashi*, which is again different because we said that we said that
the what-do-you-call-it, that it has to be directly over. But I'm just
going to read you the only way this makes sense is רש"י
*Rashi* sort of says even though it's supposed to be directly over,
maybe you can't totally exactly position it directly over, and some of
the blood, what's definitely going to happen to some of the blood
is not that it's going to go straight down, but some of
the blood is going to go across and down. Okay? And if
some of the blood is going to go across and down, then
why do we say you're getting the blood from the neck? You're
getting the blood from the air. Okay? So the only reason we're
saying you're getting the blood from the neck is because assuming anytime
it changes the vector it's like it's not direct is that, but
you know which did what did get the blood directly from the
neck? The airspace.
When it went this way, even before it went down, the airspace
got the blood directly from the neck. So even though the vessel
is getting it indirectly and that could be a problem, the airspace
of the vessel is like the vessel. And since the airspace got
it directly from the neck, it's like the vessel got it directly
from the neck. So what you see from this is that אויר
שסופו לנוח כמונח דמי *avir she-sofo lanoach kemonach dami*. If it's in
an airspace that eventually it's going to go into the vessel, it's
like it's already in the vessel. Okay? Everybody got that? So the
answer, so this is invalid for פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* because it's
like it's in the vessel, this is valid because even though it
hit the vessel indirectly, it got into the airspace directly. All right?
How does that move into the bottom?
It doesn't. We like the bottom case is like we're forgetting that.
That's probably that's definitely invalid. The more interesting case is with the
bottom, not when the bottom falls out, is it like it's already
in the vessel? And the basic answer is yes. Okay.
All right, so now תנן התם *tnan hatam*. Let's move on. נתן
ידו או רגלו עלי ירקות כדי שיעברו מים לחבית פסולים *Natan yado
o raglo alei yerakot kedei she-ya'avru mayim le-chavit pesulim*. Now we're talking
about a פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* thing, we're digressing a bit. Okay,
so if the way I transported the water from the well to
the vessel that I'm using for פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* is through
something that could become טמא tamei. *tamei* even if it's not טמא
tamei *tamei*. So what I did was I used my hand or
I used a leg and it traveled over my arm or I
used some type of vegetable leaves which are like food, like a
lettuce leaf, and they could become טמא *tamei* and through that I
transported the water from the well into the vessel, it's invalid. עלי
קנים ועלי אגוזים כשרה *Alei kanim ve-alei egozim kesherah*. If however I
used leaves from like reeds or from nuts which are not edible,
then it's okay. זה הכלל *Zeh haklal*, this is the principle: דבר
המקבל טומאה *Davar ha-mekabel tumah* if I transported it with something that
could become
טמא *tamei*, פסולים *pesulim*. but if it cannot become טמא it's okay.
מנא הני מילי, Mena hani milei, where's this from? And we're going
to see how this ties back to our point in a minute,
דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בר אבא d’amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Yose bar Abba אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says אך
מעיין ובור, Ach mayan ubor, a wellspring or a cistern מקוה מים,
mikveh mayim, a gathering of water יהיה טהור yihyeh tahor will be
pure. הוייתן, Havayatan, when you create these things that are about, you
know, that are like, you know, these gatherings of water that are
being used in ritual purposes, so הוייתן על ידי טהרה, havayatan al
yedei taharah, it has to be only through things that are טהור,
tahor, not through things that could become טמא. Now, תינח, teinech, now
תהא. tehei.
So אמר רבי חייא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya amar Rabbi
Yochanan, I just want to do this last line, זאת אומרת אוויר
כלי ככלי דמי. Zot omeret avir kli k'kli dami. Once again, we're
going to, this is the last point about this thing, the airspace
of a vessel is like a vessel. Why? How does that tell
it? Okay, so because he says, look, what's going to happen is
is that why when I use my hand to transport it, okay,
I use my hand to transport it and then it falls
from my hand into the vessel. So why don't I say wait,
first it hits the air and then the air in the vessel,
so the actual collecting of in the vessel wasn't from my hand?
The vessel actually got it from the air, okay? And if it
got it from the air, it didn't get it from a טמא
place, it got it from a טהור tahor place. The problem with
my hand is that I'm, as a person, I could be מקבל
טומאה. mekabel tumah. And we say that can't make the collection of
water. But it didn't! The air, the water came from the air,
it didn't come from my hand. So if you say that once
it goes from my hand into the airspace, it's like it went
into the vessel, that's the problem. The assumption is that the thing
that's the problem has to directly be juxtaposed to it hitting the
vessel. Okay, sort of similar to this issue. So the גמרא Gemara
says, who says? So it has this last line, so the גמרא
Gemara says, ודילמא, v'dilma,
so אמר ליה רב זירא לרבי חייא בר אבא, amar lei Rav
Zeira l'Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, ודילמא בשוטט. v'dilma b'shoteit. Who says, who
says that it went from my hand into the airspace and in
the vessel, and then it shows you the airspace is like the
vessel? Maybe it went straight into the vessel itself, right? It didn't
go, you know, went straight from my hand into the vessel, didn't
first hit the airspace, it dripped into the vessel. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, he said back to him, תרדו, tirdu, which is like, I
don't know, idiot, כדי שיעברו מים לחבית תנן. kedai sheya’avru mayim l’chavit
tenan. It says that the water should pass into the barrel, okay,
which basically does suggest not dripping but sort of suggests more streaming
in. So bottom line is what have we said here? Because we
said my, it can't go from my hand into the barrel, but
the scenario is it goes from my hand into the air and
the air into the barrel, from there you see that the airspace
is like the barrel itself. The air above a vessel is like
the, if it weren't, then it would be seen as if it
just magically came from the air into the barrel and it would
be okay. The only reason it's invalid is it's from my hand
into the airspace is like from my hand into the barrel. So
this is yet another proof that the airspace above is like the
thing, so that's why this is invalid. If this was from my
hand also, that would be invalid or whatever for the similar reason,
okay, you know, but whatever. Anyway, and that this is okay even
though it's not, even though it's indirect into the vessel, it's direct
into the airspace. All right, I think we will end with that.